<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The last declarations of the Committee of Estates now assembled in Scotland, concerning their proceedings in opposition to the late unlawfull engagement against England. Together with the articles agreed upon by the commissioners appointed by the noblemen, gentlemen, and burgesses who protested against the late engagement. And the answer thereunto.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1248</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E468_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203717</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863563</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863563</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162330</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92565)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162330)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 75:E468[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The last declarations of the Committee of Estates now assembled in Scotland, concerning their proceedings in opposition to the late unlawfull engagement against England. Together with the articles agreed upon by the commissioners appointed by the noblemen, gentlemen, and burgesses who protested against the late engagement. And the answer thereunto.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>... re-printed at London for Robert Bostock, at the signe of the Kings Head in Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>18 Octob. 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Edinburgh, printed by Evan Tyler.</note>
                  <note>Reprints "A declaration of the Committee of Estates concerning their proceedings in opposition to the late unlawfull engagement against England" by the Parliament of Scotland, and "A short declaration to the whole Kirk and kingdom concerning the present dangers and duties" by the Church of Scotland, General Assembly.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:162330:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The laſt DECLARATIONS OF THE Committee of Eſtates <hi>Now Aſſembled</hi> In SCOTLAND, <hi>Concerning</hi> Their Proceedings in oppoſition to the late unlawfull ENGAGEMENT againſt ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with</hi> The ARTICLES agreed upon by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners appointed by the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Gentlemen, and Burgeſſes who Proteſted againſt the late ENGAGEMENT. And the ANSWER thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Printed by EVAN TYLER. And Re-Printed at LONDON for <hi>Robert Boſtock,</hi> at the Signe of the Kings Head in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 18 <hi>Octob.</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:162330:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:162330:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>DECLARATION</hi> of the Committee of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates concerning their Proceedings in oppoſition to the late unlawfull Engagement againſt <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He manifold dangers to Religion, to the Kings Majeſty, to our Laws and Liberties, and to the Peace of theſe Kingdoms, are ſo manifeſt, that they cannot be hid from any, who will not wilfully ſhut their eys againſt a cleer light: and the remedies which we have taken in this extremity, wil (we doubt not) be judged by all men of common equity and underſtanding, to have been moſt neceſſary for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving Religion from ruine, and our ſelves from ſlavery and oppreſſion: Yet, to prevent m ſinformation and miſconſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, we have thought fit to publiſh a ſhort narration of the Cauſes of our late undertaking to riſe in arms, of our procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings by way of Treaty with thoſe that joyned in arms for the late Engagement againſt <hi>England,</hi> and of our reſolutions for ſetling Religion, and the Peace of this diſtracted Kingdom, and ſtrengthening the Union betwixt the Kingdoms, which are the beſt foundations of Honour and Happineſſe to the King; whoſe Throne we deſire may be eſtabliſhed in Righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>When wee look back upon ſome proceedings in our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Nation, though there wee ſee that the work of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath been much obſtructed, and many things have been done, of which we cannot approve, and wherewith God was highly diſpleaſed; yet we finde the Fountain and Spring of all our troubles mainly to ariſe at home, from the craft and malice of our Natives and Country-men. For, notwithſtanding the Right Honorable Houſes of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by their Commiſſioners to remove all differences which had ariſen betwixt them and us, and to do what-ever was juſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:162330:3"/>and Honourable for the ſatisfaction of this Kingdom: And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, had declared their readineſſe to joyn with this Kingdom in the Propoſitions agreed on by both Kingdoms, preſented to the King at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> for the making ſuch further proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings thereupon as ſhould be thought fit, for the ſpeedy ſettlement of the Peace of both Kingdoms, and preſervation of the Union according to the Covenant and Treaties. And further, to give ſatisfaction in all things which ſhould be judged neceſſary for the Peace of both Kingdoms, not intrenching upon the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Intereſt of the Kingdom, and Priviledges of the Parliament of <hi>England:</hi> yet many of this Nation having entered into a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Aſſociation and wicked Combination, did joyn together in Arms under the command of the Duke of <hi>Hamiltoun,</hi> for pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of an unlawfull Engagement againſt our neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>England,</hi> contrary to the ends of the ſolemn League and Covenant, the manifold admonitions and exhortations of all the faithfull Miniſters of the Goſpel, the warnings and Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly, 1647. As likewiſe againſt the unanimous proceedings of the late Generall Aſſembly in this yeer 1648; againſt the Judgement and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations of many Members of Parliament, who have been moſt conſtant in the Cauſe, and to preſerve the Union betwixt the Kingdoms; and generally againſt the minds and judgements of all the well-affected in the Kingdom: And further, brought over from <hi>Ireland</hi> ſome Regiments of the Scots Army to joyn with them in this Engagement, contrary to the Treaty betwixt the Kingdoms of the 7 of <hi>July</hi> 1642. And having joyned in an unlawfull Aſſociation with the Malignants of <hi>England,</hi> did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy ſome of them to ſurprize and take the Gariſons of <hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Carlile</hi> (and yet profeſſed openly before the World, they were ignorant who had done it) contrary to the large Treaty betwixt the Kingdoms, and the Treaty of the 29 of <hi>November</hi> 1643. And when by miſerable and cruell oppreſſion of the people of God in this Kingdom they had gathered together a numerous Army, they took poſſeſſion of the Gariſons of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> and <hi>Carlile,</hi> and in an hoſtile manner entered into our Neighbour Nation; where the Lord of Hoſts poured forth his Wrath and Indignation upon them for their lyes and hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:162330:3"/>as was before threatned by many of the faithfull ſervants of God in this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>While theſe men were invading <hi>England,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Lanerick</hi> and others engaged in the ſame Deſigne, ſtayed at home to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe this Kingdom; and under a pretence of raiſing a Guard for the Prince, did begin a new Levie of Forces, whereby they might be able to ſend ſupply to their Army in <hi>England,</hi> if need were; but principally to bear down the godly and wel-affected in this Kingdom, and force upon them unlawfull Bands and Oathes, which they deviſed to be engines and ſnares to compell men to make Shipwrack of their Conſciences, by joyning with all their wicked ways, or in caſe they refuſed to take thoſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed Oaths, and ſubſcribe their Bands, that then they might not onely be uncapable of all publick Truſt, but be eſteemed and uſed as Enemies to Religion, King and Kingdom; and ſo every way to oppreſſe all honeſt men in their Perſons, Eſtates and Conſciences, as nothing was to be expected from their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to theſe who deſired to fear the Lord, and adhere to their firſt Principles, but ſlavery and ruine: for they having ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed the Parliament till <hi>March</hi> 1650, had aſſumed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves an Arbitrary Power, that in the mean time they might rule at their pleaſure, and make ſuch alterations in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as they thought fit. Upon news of the defeat of their Army, they did give out Commiſſions to prime Incendiaries, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged ſuch as were eminent and active in Rebellion, under the conduct of <hi>James Graham</hi> late Earl of <hi>Montroſe,</hi> to riſe in Arms; and ſent directions to the Forces under the command of <hi>George Monro,</hi> which had invaded <hi>England,</hi> but were not preſent at the Fight, and other Officers and Souldiers who eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from it, to return to this Kingdom, that ſo by their conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the Forces lately raiſed, they might have a new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my on foot to proſecute their former deſigne, and to tyrannize over this Kingdom, as is evident from their Letters of the 28 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> ſent to the Earl of <hi>Marſhall</hi> Vicount of <hi>Dudhope, Clerk Regiſter,</hi> and <hi>George Monro,</hi> (ten days after the defeat of their Army in <hi>England</hi>) wherein ſpeaking of the Engagement, they declare their reſolution to recruit their Regiments, and to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard their Lives and Fortunes, and all that was deareſt unto
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162330:4"/>them for carrying on againſt all oppoſition whatſoever that pious and loyall Service, and that they and many others of this Kingdom did intend not to live and out-live it: By all which, and many other their like proceedings expreſſed in the Declarations of the Generall Aſſembly and their Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, it is ſufficiently evident that Religion hath not only been endangered, but the whole work of Reformation in theſe Kingdoms for theſe ten years paſt hath been very neer to bee wholly overturned, our Laws and Liberties almoſt deſtroyed, Authority weakned, the perſon of the King put in hazard, and his reſtitution (which they pretended) rendred more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, and endeavours uſed to break the Union and Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Kingdoms, and to continue (ſo far as was in their power) a laſting War betwixt this Kingdom and our neighbour Nation with whom we are joyned in Covenant.</p>
            <p>This being the true eſtate of affairs, We did find it moſt neceſſary for us to joyn in Armes together againſt theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant breakers and their Adherents who had invaded <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and were diſturbing the Peace of this Kingdom (and who under a ſpecious pretence of ſeeking the Kings Honour, Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Safety, were ſeeking their own Honour and baſe private ends, and have made the Kings condition harder then ever it was before) this courſe being the only means which was left us whreeby to endeavour the preſervation of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, our native Country, and the Peace and Union betwixt the Kingdoms, and our own Conſciences being ready to condemn us if we ſhould ſit ſtill and ſuffer Religion to be ruined, <hi>England</hi> to be further provoked (by detaining their Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) and this Kingdom to be enſlaved and brought under the yoke of a perpetuall bondage.</p>
            <p>When we had put our ſelves in a poſture for our own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence neer <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Crawford,</hi> the Earl of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerik, George Monro,</hi> and other Commanders of the Forces joyned with them, having marched to <hi>Inneresk,</hi> ſent us ſome Articles upon which they deſired to Treat, for remove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all differences betwixt us; but theſe Demands being very unreaſonable and inconſiſtent with Religion, the Covenant and Treaties betwixt the Kingdoms, We refuſed to admit
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:162330:4"/>them to be the ſubject of a Treaty; yet were content if they had any other thing to propound which might conduce to the ſetling of Truth and Peace according to the Covenant, to appoint ſome from us to Treat with the like number autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized by them, at any place equally diſtant from both Armies. Whereupon they profeſſed a readineſſe to have all differences ended by a Treaty, that an inteſtine war might be prevented; but they aſſigned ſo ſhort Dyets for us to return our Anſwers about the neceſſary circumſtances to be agreed on before a Treaty could begin, as the time was elapſed before we could be well conveened; and then they took the advantage of marching away, whileſt we continued in our Quarters in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of a Treaty, by which means they gained the paſſe at <hi>Sterling,</hi> and ſurprized our Forces there, killing ſome, and taking others Priſoners when they were in ſecurity being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſed that there was a Treaty betwixt us; All this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, ſo deſirous were we of the peace of this almoſt ruined Kingdom, as paſſing over all the provocations given unto us, we readily entertained all proffers to Treat, and upon the 14. of <hi>September,</hi> Commiſſioners on both ſides met at <hi>Woodſide,</hi> together with ſome Miniſters and Elders from the Commiſſion of the Kirk; but after three daies debate that Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (during which their Army was grievouſly plundering the Countrey) produced little elſe but delaies, they refuſing to accept of any conditions without rewards for their ſervice, Liberty to tranſport the Iriſh Forces in a body to <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for their Lives, Eſtates, Honours, Fortunes and places, and aſſurance that none who had been acceſſory to the late En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement ſhould be queſtioned either by us, or by the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> for any thing done by them in relation thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, which was impoſſible for us to grant without involving our ſelves in the guilt of the Engagement, and giving occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of quarrell againſt us to our neighbour Nation, in whoſe names we could promiſe nothing without their advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. And here we cannot but remark, that theſe Lords and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who in Parliament and otherwiſe, pretended ſo great a zeal for his Majeſties Honour, Freedom and Safety, yet in all their demands to us in this Treaty, they never made the leaſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:162330:5"/>deſire of any thing for the King, but were ready to cloſe an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with us when ever they could get ſatisfaction in what concerned their own Honour, Freedom and Intereſt.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as we underſtood that the Forces of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> were come to the Borders, for purſuit of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy, and reducing the Garriſons of <hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile,</hi> We wrote a Letter from <hi>Falkirk</hi> to the Commander in chief of theſe Forces, and ſent two from us with Inſtructions to acquaint him with the eſtate of our affairs, particularly our proceedings in the Treaty, and to aſſure them that we would contribute our utmoſt endeavours for the reſtitution of the Towns of <hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Carlile</hi> to the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> to whom they do of right belong: In return whereunto we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from Lieut. Generall <hi>Cromwel</hi> a Letter to this purpoſe, That upon the defeat of the Forces of the Duke of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton</hi> they had received in command that they ſhould proſecute the Victory, untill the Enemy were put out of a condition of growing into a new Army, and the Garriſons of <hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Carlile</hi> were reduced, in purſuance of which commands they had reſolved to advance into <hi>Scotland</hi> with their Army for obtaining their Garriſons, and that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy might be the ſooner brought to a ſubmiſſion to reaſonable conditions, withall ingaging themſelves that ſo ſoon as they ſhould know from us that the Enemy ſhould yeeld to theſe things we had propoſed to them, and the Garriſons of <hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Carlile</hi> were delivered, they ſhould forthwith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of this Kingdom: after the receipt of this Letter, We ſent ſome of our number with power and inſtructions to do their utmoſt endeavour for obtaining the Towns of <hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Carlile</hi> to be ſurrendred to him for the uſe of the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſes of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and to repreſent our earneſt deſire and firm reſolution to preſerve inviolable the Union betwixt the Kingdoms according to the Covenant and Treaties; and ſince they had reſolved in obedience to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands laid upon them, to ſend Forces into this Kingdom for purſuing the common Enemy; therefore to deſire that thoſe which ſhould be ſent might be ſuch as would give no offence or ſcandal to the Miniſtry and well-affected in this Kingdom.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:162330:5"/>
            <p> Upon the 18. of <hi>September</hi> ſome Propoſitions were ſent unto us from thoſe at <hi>Sterling,</hi> to which we returned an Anſwer upon the 20. And after a new meeting at <hi>Kirklistoun</hi> with Commiſſioners from them, Articles of Agreement were drawn up and ſubſcribed by the Commiſſioners on both ſides, which are now publiſhed in print: In all which proceedings we have ſtudyed to ſet before our eyes the Honor of God, and the good of Religion, the preſervation of our Laws and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and of the Union betwixt the Kingdoms. And to the end it may further appear to this Kingdom and to all the World, that no ſiniſter end or worldly deſign for ſelf-intereſt, hath ſtirred us up to this courſe, we do declare.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, that we have both matter of deep humiliation before God, and thankſgiving to him when we conſider his gracious diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards us, in preſerving a remnant from following the evil courſes of the time, and that he was pleaſed ſo ſoon after a great defection and backſliding in the Land, to put us into a condition to reſiſt the force and fury of our Enemies, whom neither Chriſtian duty in ſo dear a Sunſhine of the Goſpel, nor natural affection to their native Country, could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain from horrid impieties and intolerable oppreſſions. And we do freely acknowledg that it had bin juſt with the Lord to ſuffer us to lie ſtill under that yoke of bondage, which we had wreathed upon our necks with our own hands, by compliance with Malignants and Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant courſes, not truſting the Lord with his own work, and reſting on his ſtrength, but following the rules of carnal policy, when ever we were brought into ſtraights. It is the deſire of our Souls that for the future we may amend, and it ſhall be our conſtant ſtudy, with Gods aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, to avoid the rocks on which we were ready to ſplit, that we may neither upon the one hand put confidence in the arm of fleſh, and other wordly advantages when things are proſperous, nor upon the other, comply with the Enemies of the cauſe when we are low, but in all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and conditions to put our truſt in God Almighty, the Lord of Hoſt, who alſo is only wiſe to give Counſel.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That whatſoever Power God hath already, or ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after put into our hands, we ſhall improve it for ſetling and propagating Religion, and promoting the work of Reformation according to the Covenant, and in particular, to have the Liberties of the Kirk ratified, which have bin many ways incroached upon and violated, as is particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly inſtanced in the Declaration of the General Aſſembly.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:162330:6"/>
            <p> Thirdly, To vindicate and eſtabliſh the liberty and property of the Subjects, who have bin moſt grievouſly oppreſſed in their Conſciences, Perſons and Eſtates.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That we ſhall indeavor the Kings Majeſties Reſtitution to the exerciſe of his Royal Power, as ſoon as he ſhall give ſecurity for ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Religion in the manner expreſſed in the deſires of the late Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Kirk, and ſhall give ſatisfaction in ſuch other things as ſhall be found neceſſary for the peace and ſafety of the Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, That the late unlawful Engagement againſt our Neighbour Nation of <hi>England,</hi> with whom we are joyned in League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, may be diſclaimed and diſavowed by the Supream Authority of this Kingdom, it being moſt deſtructive to Religion, and to the Peace and Happineſs of theſe Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, To ſtrengthen and confirm the Peace and Union between the Kingdoms, which the Malignant Party hath ſo much endeavored to break and diſſolve.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, That we ſhall endeavor to purge out of all the Judicatories in the Land, Malignancy and Prophaneſs, and uſe all other good means that Juſtice may be equally and impartially adminiſtred to all the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in the Kingdom, and that a more effectual courſe may be taken throughout the whole Kingdom then heretofore, for puniſhing and ſuppreſſing all Prophaneſs, Malignancy and Impiety.</p>
            <p>Eightly, All means having bin uſed with great induſtry, to get Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants choſen to be Commiſſioners to the laſt Parliament, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs mens minds when they came to the Parliament, from which as a Fountain have iſſued all our troubles and diſtractions. That we will faithfully indeavor to have a free Parliament, conſiſting of ſuch perſons as have not bin acceſſary to, and furtherers of the late Engagement, for which end we do again hereby require that in the Election of Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners from Burroughs and Shires to the Parliament, the rules and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſet down in our Acts of the 22. <hi>September</hi> laſt, and the fourth of this inſtant month of <hi>October,</hi> may be punctually obſerved throughout the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And we call the ſearcher of hearts to record, that theſe are our real and true intentions, and that we do not, nor ſhall by the Grace of God purſue any private ends or intereſts of our own. And we truſt, the Lord our God who knoweth the ſincerity of our reſolutions, who hath alſo had mercy upon us, and hath begun to do ſo graciouſly for us, will
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:162330:6"/>aſsiſt us herein until his work ſhall be accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>And now laſt of all, ſince it is agreed upon in the Treaty, that all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and differences about Religion be referred to the determination of the General Aſſembly or their Commiſsioners, and that all Civil que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and differences be referred to the determination of a Parliament, which is to ſit down before the 10. of <hi>January</hi> next: We do exhort and require all and every one of the Subjects within this Kingdom, to live peaceable and quietly, and to wait patiently for the determination aforeſaid, but in caſe any ſhall not reſt ſatisfied with, or ſhall re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le from the ſaid agreement, and ſhall continue, or riſe in Arms, or levy any For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces without Warrant from the Committee of Eſtates as it is now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, conſiſting of perſons not acceſſory to the late Engagement. We do declare that they ſhall be eſteemed Enemies to Religion, the King and Kingdom, and puniſhed as wilful diſturbers of the Peace of the Kingdom.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. Thomas Henderſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <head>A ſhort Declaration to the whole Kirk and Kingdom, concerning preſent Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Duties.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Edinb.</hi> 
                  <date>9. September 1648.</date> 
                  <hi>Ante meridiem.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>ALbeit the ſad and dangerous condition wherein this Kirk and Kingdom is now caſt, by the publick Reſolutions and practiſed of theſe who have ingaged in War againſt the Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> do proclaim unto all the lowers of Religion and the Country, what is needful to be done in this day of diſtreſs: Yet for the better infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Lords people, we conceive it neceſſary, ſhortly for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:162330:7"/>ſent to declare what we hold incombent in duty to all theſe who would not betray the cauſe of God, and render themſelves ſlaves to the tyranny and luſt of ungodly and Malignant men, hoping in a ſhort time to make known our thoughts of theſe particulars more fully.</p>
            <p>When the diſ-affected and prevailing party in the Parliament of this Kingdom did manifeſt head-ſtrong reſolutions to make War upon <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> under a pretext of ſuppreſsing Sectaries; But in effect, to diſſolve the Union betwixt the Kingdoms, and to reſtore the King to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of his Arbitrary Government, and make way for promoving of the Deſigns of the Malignant party in both Nations, juſt and neceſſary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires relating unto the grounds of an ingagement, and unto the ſecuring of Religion, were preſented unto their Lordſhips by the Commiſsion of the former General Aſſembly: But theſe deſires were altogether ſlighted, and an ingagement reſolved upon ſuch grounds as are contrary to the Word of God, and do infer the breach of all the Articles of the Solemn League and Covenant, as is clearly holden forth in the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the laſt General Aſſembly; wherein alſo may be ſeen the great incroachments that are made upon the Liberties of the Kirk: Neither was there any regard had unto the diſſent and Proteſtation of a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number of Members of Parliament, who had bin moſt active and ſtraight in the Cauſe from the beginning; nor unto the Petitions and Supplications of many Synods and Presbyteries, and of the well affected people of the Land, who were ſeeking ſatisfaction to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences: But inſtead of a ſatisfactory anſwer, the ingagement which was wickedly reſolved, was violently carried on by moſt ſtrange plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and cruel oppreſsion, eſpecially of theſe who did it upon no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ground then out of fear to ſin againſt God: And as though it had bin too little to force obedience unto their unlawful Reſolutions and Acts; the Committee of Eſtates have urged and preſſed the ſubſcribing of a Band and Declaration of Parliament, wherein men are obliged to acknowledg the juſtice and equity of all the Acts, Concluſions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions thereof, or if they refuſe, are to be eſteemed Eenemies to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and their Country: And after that the Committee of Eſtates had ſent ſuch an Army unto <hi>England,</hi> as by the leaders therof, was profeſſed to be ſo conſiderable, as was ſufficient to proſecute their Reſolutions in that Kingdom, without any further ſupply of Forces from this: Yet they have reſolved upon, and proſecuted a new levy, with no leſs vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence then the former, that they may wreith the yoke of their oppreſsion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:162330:7"/>upon the necks of the Lords people, and bring the whole Kingdom in flavery and bondage: And though the Lord hath declared his wrath from heaven aginſt theſe their reſolutions and proceedings, by bringing their Army to ſo ſudden and ſhameful on overthrow; yet do they ſtill adhere unto, and purſue the ſame deſigns, and have not only brought within the bowels of this Kingdom the remnant of that godleſs and prophane Army, but have given Commiſsion alſo to claſſed incendiaries and Rebels who ſerved under the conduct of <hi>James Grahame</hi> to raiſe Forces, and by the whole tenure of their carriage, do make it appear to all who have eyes to ſee, that they do intend rather to involve the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in blood, then to be reſtrained in the perſuit of their former wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed reſolutions.</p>
            <p>Therefore albeit the thoughts of peace be precious unto us, and that we wiſh and exhort every one to follow peace with all men as much as is poſsible; yet looking upon the eminent dangers that threaten Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the grievous oppreſsions that lies upon the Lords people in their Conſciences, Perſons and Eſtates, and the many fearful evils, that threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en both Kirk and Kingdom, if the remnant of theſe mens wrath be not reſtrained: We conceive that all the people of God are obliged and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged by Covenant, with their Lives and Eſtates, to endeavor and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue theſe following ends, and to oppoſe all the Enemies and Adverſaries thereof; Firſt, Becauſe Religion is of all things the moſt excellent and precious, the ſecuring thereof is to be moſt in our thoughts, and in the indeavors of all men, that it may be preſerved unto us, and tranſmitted unto our poſterity, in purity. Secondly, All are bound to defend and maintain the Liberties of the Kirk, which is the Houſe of God, and the ground and Pillar of Truth. Thirdly, All are bound to vindicate the Liberties of the Subjects, in all theſe things which concern their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, Perſons and Eſtates. Fourthly, There is no leſs obligation, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to maintain the Union betwixt the Kingdoms, and to avoid every thing that may weaken the ſame, or involve us in any meaſure of acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion unto the guilt of theſe who have invaded the Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi> Fifthly, All are to indeavor the Kings Majeſties Reſtitution to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his Royal Power, as ſoon as he ſhall give ſecurity for Religion, in the manner expreſſed in the deſires of the late Commiſsion of the Kirk, and ſhall give ſatisfaction in ſuch other things as are neceſſary for the peace and ſafety of the Kingdom. Sixthly, All are to take a more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual courſe then heretofore, for puniſhing and ſuppreſſing of all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignancy,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:162330:8"/>injuſtice, iniquity, prophaneſs and impiety, and to indeavor, that the beſt and fitteſt remedies be applied for taking away the cauſes of theſe evils, and advancing <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> in the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd,</hi> and that thoſe men who have been formerly inſtrumental in our preſent <hi>miſeries</hi> and <hi>calamities,</hi> be not again admitted unto any ſuch truſt or power as may enable them to involve the Land in the ſame or the like Evils.</p>
            <p>Theſe things are of ſuch importance and conſequence as that we know not what can be expected without them but a continuance and increaſe of our preſent miſeries and calamities; And therefore ſeeing the Lord hath now put into the hands of his people ſuch an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and made many willing in this day of his power: We do exhort and beſeech all men, throughout the Land, by the mercies of God who hath not given us over unto death, but left us a nail in his holy place, that they would ſeriouſly mind, and to the utmoſt of their power pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer theſe ends againſt all lets and impediments whatſoever, and oppoſe all theſe who ſtand for the engagement. In the beginning of this work the Lord ſtirred up the ſpirits of his people to joyn together and defend themſelves againſt tyranny and oppreſſion in theſe things which concerned their conſciences and liberties; and albeit their power was but ſmall, and the ſtrength of adverſaries great, yet becauſe they did their duty in the ſimplicity of their hearts, and truſted in the name of the Lord, he was pleaſed to make the enemies melt as wax before the fire, and to vaniſh as ſmoak before the wind: And if after ſo many rich experiences of his aſſiſtance and rare teſtimonies of his loving kindneſs, and great deliverances out of troubles and ſolemn ingagements by vows and Covenants, we ſhould ſit ſtill, or comply with thoſe who have carryed on the ingagement in a time that threatens ſo much danger un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Religion, and ſo iminent ruin to our liberties, perſons, and eſtates, we could not but be exceedingly guilty before the Lord, and deſerve to be plagued as betrayers of the cauſe of God, and of the ſafety both of Kirk and State: Let us therefore ariſe, and do our duty, and the Lord of hoſts, who hath already broken the power, and pride of our adverſaries, ſhall be with us.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:162330:8"/>
            <head>Articles concluded upon by the Officers and Soldiers, now in Arms by authority of the Parliament of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE being ſervants to the <hi>State,</hi> and unwilling to ingage in a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil War, do conceive our ſelves obliged to remit the ways of proſecuting of all duties to Religion, and to our King, to the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> And let them move in it as they will be anſwerable to God: Our lives ſhall ever be ready to be expoſed to all hazards for the good of both; and if all duties for them, and for our <hi>friends releaſe</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> ſhall now be deſerted, let the blame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and men lie upon the obſtructors of it: And if no further <hi>uſe</hi> be made of our <hi>ſervice,</hi> We do demand,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>ſecurity</hi> be given to all, who are or have been ingaged in this <hi>ſervice,</hi> for their <hi>Perſons, Honors,</hi> and <hi>Eſtates,</hi> whereby they may be free from all dangers, prejudices, and cenſures whatſoever, whether Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical or Civil, for their <hi>acceſſion</hi> to the late <hi>Engagement,</hi> or any thing done by them relating thereunto, or to this <hi>ſervice</hi> for our own <hi>defence:</hi> And this to be confirmed by <hi>Parliament,</hi> or the lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That in regard of our extraordinary charges and loſs; one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths pay be inſtantly delivered unto us, for payment of the <hi>Iriſh For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and that Boats and Ships preſently be provided for their tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation into <hi>Ireland:</hi> And for preventing all diſorders upon their march through the Weſt-Country by <hi>Free-quartering,</hi> We do deſire that a <hi>regular courſe</hi> may be taken for their <hi>entertainment</hi> during their abode there, which ſhall be no longer then <hi>wind</hi> and <hi>weather</hi> ſhall ſerve, and Boats be provided to tranſport them.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:162330:9"/> III. That one <hi>Moneths means</hi> be provided for the <hi>Scottiſh Forces<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and that they be not disbanded until the <hi>Iriſh Forces</hi> be tranſported; and that <hi>ſufficient pledges</hi> be delivered for <hi>performance</hi> of what is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. And that our disbanding and tranſportation be done by <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Committee of Eſtates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>reaſonable demands</hi> being performed, We the <hi>Iriſh</hi> are ready inſtantly to march towards any part of the <hi>Weſt coaſt</hi> which ſhall be thought moſt fit for our tranſportation into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and we of the Scottiſh, inſtantly to disband: Otherwiſe, rather then expoſe our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes</hi> to the <hi>mercy</hi> of any, by the want of fitting <hi>aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances</hi> for what is paſt, or the loſs of our Honors by deſerting the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> of thoſe commanded by, or joyned with us, We are reſolved to ſacrifice our ſelves at the <hi>deareſt rates</hi> we can; And take God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs how free we are of the <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>conſequences</hi> that may follow thereupon.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Stirling</hi> 
                  <date>18. <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1648.</date>
               </dateline>

               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed by Warrant and Command of the Officers now in Arms by the Authority of Parliament,</hi> Jo: SPALDGUGE.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>We have appointed our Commiſſioners to ſtay no longer then ſix o clock at night, to morrow the 19. and that the Treaty ſhall then end; and that the Ceſſation ſhall expire eight hours thereafter, unleſs the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires</hi> before-mentioned be fully granted.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="answers">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:162330:9"/>
            <head>The Anſwer of the Noblemen and Gentlemen now in Armes for the Covenant, to the Articles of the Officers and Souldiers that joyned in the late unlawfull Engagement againſt <hi>England,</hi> and now continue in Armes to diſturb the peace of this Kingdom.</head>
            <div type="answer">
               <p>WEE have conſidered the deſires of the Officers and Souldiers at <hi>Sterlin,</hi> and do return this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; That the Imputation of neglecting dutyes to Religion and to the King mentioned in the Preface to the Articles cannot be charged on Us, who have never been wanting in the uſe of all lawfull meanes, to proſecute the ends of our ſolemne League and Covenant: But upon thoſe who joyned in proſecution of the late unlawfull Engagement againſt our neighbour Nation of <hi>England,</hi> which hath beene deſtructive to all theſe ends.</p>
               <p>Touching the firſt article, Wee referr you to the anſwer given in our former papers, and do here again declare, that we ſhall not challenge, nor incite any other to challenge any of your number for their lives and eſtates, but ſhall endeavour to ſecure them ſo far as we can without approbation of their actions, or the breach of Covenant and Treaties. As for that which concerns exemption from Church-cenſures, we cannot meddle therein without breach of Covenant, but muſt referr you to the Iudicatories of the Kirk, to whom you may make your own addreſſe, and receive their anſwer.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:162330:10"/>
               <p> Concerning the ſecond and third articles, we refer you to the anſwer given by our Commiſſioners to the Commiſſioners on your ſide, which was, that we held it unreaſonable that they ſhould deſire any thing from us, or any other who adhere to us, for ſatisfaction of their Officers and Souldiers, becauſe we will not involve our ſelves in any thing which may import an acceſſion to the late engagement or may be the ground of a quarrell to <hi>England</hi> againſt this Kingdome; but if they had reall inclinations to Peace, they and their adherents might without our accesſion thereunto take courſe amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for giving ſatisfaction to their Officers and Souldiers, and therefore did deſire (and do now again renew the ſame) that all their forces, and the forces of theſe who adhere unto them, may be disbanded betwixt and the twenty fifth, or at furtheſt the twenty eight day of this moneth of <hi>September,</hi> and that none of them be found together after that time, in Troops, Companies, or Regiments; and wee ſhall betwixt and the ſaid day, disband all our Forces, and none of them after that time ſhall, bee found in Troopes Companyes, or Regiments; for the punctuall performance whereof on both ſides, mutuall pledges are to bee given; and further we cannot ſay in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to theſe articles.</p>
               <p>If you ſhall not agree to the Deſires made in our laſt papers of the 16 of this inſtant, and not reſt ſatisfied with theſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, but ſhall continue in Armes to the diſturbance of the Peace of this Kingdom, and perſiſt in the courſes in which you are now engaged, contrary to the Declarations of the Generall Aſſembly &amp; their Commiſſioners, we do hereby certify unto you, that all who have been active in the late <hi>Engagement,</hi> as well choſe in <hi>England</hi> as thoſe in this Kingdom, and all ſuch as have or ſhall hereafter joyn with you, are to be declared enemies to both Kingdoms; and that this Kingdom will be neceſſitated to concurre with the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> for puniſhing them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly as breakers of the Covenant and Treaties; and wee leave it to you ſeriouſly to conſider whether the wayes and courſes you are upon, bee really for the good of the King and this Kingdom, or a ſafe way for the releef of your friends that are priſoners in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:162330:10"/>
               <p> We do declare that unleſſe the Deſires contayned in our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the 16 of this inſtant, and in this paper, be clearly and poſitively agreed unto, and wee advertiſed thereof before Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the 22 of this inſtant, at twelve of the clock in the day, that then the Treaty ſhall end, and that the Ceſſation from acts of hoſtility and marching of forces ſhall expire eight houres thereafter.</p>
               <closer>
                  <date>
                     <hi>September</hi> 20. 1648:</date>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Subſcribed by command of the Noblemen and Gentlemen now in Arms for the Covenant.</hi> Mr Tho: Henderſon.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 22 September 1648.</head>
               <p>VVHereas many within this kingdom have joyned in Armes for proſecuting an unlawfull Engagement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Neighbour Nation of <hi>England,</hi> contrary to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant, and Treaties between the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; the Warnings and Declarations of the Commiſſion of the Generall Aſſembly 1647. And likewiſe againſt the unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous proceedings and Declaritions of the late Generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and their Commiſſioners. And whereas God hath evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently manifeſted his diſpleaſure and wrath againſt their ſinfull wayes and proceedings, in oppreſſing the well-affected in this Kingdom, invading the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> by Routing and Defeating their Army there: and now ſome of their Army have returned to this Kingdom, and joyned with others their aſſociate to diſturb the peace thereof: By which their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and actions, the work of Reformation of Religion hath been almoſt wholly overturned, the Liberty of the Subject very near deſtroyed, Authority weakned, the Perſon of the King
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:162330:11"/>put in hazzard, the union betwixt the Kingdoms endeavoured o be broken, occaſion of quarrell given to our neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and this Kingdom b ought to ſo ſad and deplorable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as (if the Lord in mercy prevent not) Famine and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation is like to bee added to all our troubles and miſeries. Therefore to prevent the emminent dangers to Religion, and to the King, for ſetling the peace of this greatly diſtracted Kingdom; and to the end the affaires of this Kingdom may not be managed by ſuch perſons as the kingdom of <hi>England</hi> do eſteem enemies for their concurrence in the late Engagement: The Committee of Eſtates conſiſting of ſuch perſons as were nominated to be on the Commiſſion of Parliament, and did diſ aſſent in Parliament from, and proteſt againſt the late un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Engagement, Do Declare that they are reſolved to act and direct in the publique affaires by vertue of the authority of that nomination of the Parliament, and their legall Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in it: and that in acting and directing, they reſolve to proceed with the advice and conſent of ſuch Members of the late Parliament, as did concurre with them in the ſaid Proteſtation, and do now concurre in armes in proſecuting of the ſame; as alſo with the advice and conſent of ſuch two Commiſſioners, and one Burgeſſe as ſhall be entruſted reſpectively by the Shires and Burghs joyning with us in armes for the Covenant; and that they will not admit into their Counſels, or Committees, any perſons who have concurred in armes or counſell for the late unlawfull Engagement, or who have ſubſcribed the Bond, or ſworn, or ſubſcribed any Oath, or Declaration for proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that Engagement. And further, that they will admit none who have been ayding, or ſhall be ayding or aſsiſting to, or abetting and agenting for theſe who are now joyned in arms with the Earl of <hi>Crawford,</hi> Earl of <hi>Glencairn,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lanerk,</hi> Lord <hi>Sinclair,</hi> Lord Regiſter, <hi>George Monro,</hi> and their adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, nor any ſuch as have, or ſhall declare their judgement againſt this cauſe and our proceedings in purſuance thereof: and we ordaine theſe Preſents to bee publiſhed: and alſo to be Printed that none pretend ignorance.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Mr. <hi>Tho: Henderſon.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:162330:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 22. September, 1648.</head>
               <p>THe Committee of Eſtates conſidering that the putting of the diſ-affected and Malignant Perſons in places of truſt and power in the ſeverall Shires ond Burghs of this Kingdom, hath been one of the greateſt cauſes which hath brought all theſe evils upon this Kingdom; and for the reaſons contained in the former act, do therefore find it neceſſary to require; And doe hereby Command and require the ſeverall Shires in the Election of their Commisſioners to Parliament, and Burghs in election of their Commisſioners to Parliament, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Counſell, that they make choice of none, but ſuch as have continued conſtant and faithfull in this Cauſe: And that they will not admit any to be in the former places of Truſt, Commiſsions, Magiſtracy or Counſells who have concurred in Arms or Counſell for the late unlawfull engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or who have ſubſcribed the Bond, or ſworne, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed any Oath or Declaration for proſecuting that engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And further that they will admit none who have been aiding, or ſhall be aiding, or aſsiſting to, or abetting and agenting for theſe who are now joyned in armes with the Earls of <hi>Crawford,</hi> Earle of <hi>Glencairn</hi> Earle of <hi>Lanerk</hi> Lord <hi>Sinclair,</hi> Lord Regiſter, <hi>George Monro,</hi> and their adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, nor any ſuch as have, or ſhall declare their judgement againſt the cauſe and our proceedings in purſuance thereof. And we ordaine theſe Preſents to be publiſhed at the Merkat Croſſe of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and other places needfull: and alſo to be Printed that none pretend ignorance.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Mr. <hi>Tho: Henderſon.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:162330:12"/>
            <head>Articles agreed on by the Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners appointed by the Noblemen, Gentlemen, and Burgeſſes who proteſted againſt the late Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and are now in Arms in and about <hi>Edingburgh:</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">And by the Commiſſioners appointed by the Noblemen, Gentlemen and Officers of the Scotiſh and Iriſh Forces that proſecutes the Engagement, and are now in Armes in and about <hi>Stirling:</hi> And ſubſcribed in the name of thoſe that entruſted them and their Adherents reſpectively.</head>
            <p n="1">I. IT is agreed, That for eaſing the burthens of the Kingdom, and to prevent Famine and Deſolation, all the Forces under the Commands of the Earl of <hi>Crawford,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lanerk, George Monro<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and all Forces having Commiſſion from any of the Committee of Eſtates that were for the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and all others whom they can ſtop or let, whether in the Field, or in the Garriſons of <hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Carlile,</hi> or other Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons within this Kingdom on this ſide of <hi>Tay,</hi> be disbanded betwixt and the firſt day of <hi>October</hi> next: And that none of them be ſeen after the ſaid day in Troops Companies or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments; And that all the Forces of their Adherents, whether
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:162330:12"/>in Field or in Garriſon, be-north <hi>Tay,</hi> and in the Highlands and Iles bee disbanded betwixt and the tenth of <hi>October</hi> next. And that none of them be ſeen after the ſaid day in Troops, Companies or Regiments.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That all Forces under the Command of his Excellency the Earl of <hi>Leven,</hi> and Lievtenant Generall <hi>David Leſly</hi> be alſo disbanded betwixt and the ſaid firſt day of <hi>October,</hi> excepting the number of one thouſand Foot, and five hundred Horſe, which are to be kept untill the disbanding of the forces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>north <hi>Tay,</hi> and the <hi>Highlands</hi> and <hi>Iles.</hi> And that then the ſaid 1000 Foot and 500 Horſes, ſhall be disbanded betwixt and the ſaid tenth day of <hi>October,</hi> and that mutuall Pledges be given for performance thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That the ſecuring and ſetling of Religion at home, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the work of Reformation abroad in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> be referred to the determination of the Generall Aſſembly, or their Commiſſioners, and all Civill queſtions and differences whatſoever bee referred to the determination of a Parliament to ſit down before the tenth of <hi>January</hi> next.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That to prevent the Immenent dangers to Religion, and a quarrell with our neighbour Nation, in the mean time untill the meeting of a Parliament. That all ſuch as have been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in publick place or truſt, and have been acceſſory to the late engagement, ſhall forbeare the exerciſe of their places, and not come to the Committee of Eſtates, to the end the Committee of Eſtates may onely conſiſt of ſuch Members of Parliament as diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſented from, and proteſted in Parliament againſt he late engagement; and in caſe any of the ſaid Forces under the Command of the Earl of <hi>Craford,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lanerk, George Monro,</hi> and their adherents, or any other Forces not under their Command ſhall continue in Arms, and not disband at the dayes appointed. That then the ſaid Committee of Eſtates conſtituted as aforeſaid, ſhall continue or raiſe Forces to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the ſame.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:162330:13"/> V. That theſe things being agreed to, and the Forces under the Earl of <hi>Craford,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lanerk, George Monro</hi> and their adherents now at <hi>Sterlin</hi> being disbanded; To the end it may appear, that we are onely ſeeking the publick good, and not the ruine of particular perſons or their Eſtates, as hath been miſreported. Wee the Committee of Eſtates conſtituted as is before expreſſed, Doe hereby declare for our Selves, and all that adhere unto us, That we ſhall neither Challenge, nor Incite any others to Challenge, any who have been acceſſory to this late Engagement and ſervice, to take away their Lives, Eſtates Titles of Honour, or the freedome of their Perſons, provided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, that no other ſhall have the benefit of this Treaty, but theſe who being on this ſide of <hi>Tay</hi> ſhall betwixt and the firſt of <hi>October</hi> next, and theſe be-north <hi>Tay,</hi> who ſhall betwixt and the tenth of <hi>October</hi> next declare under their hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing to the Lord Chancellour or Preſident of the Committee of Eſtates now at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> That they do accept of and ſubmit to this preſent agreement.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. It is further agreed that all Priſoners of this Warre on both ſides taken ſince the 25 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> be preſently releaſed.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Subſcribed</hi> 
                  <date>26. <hi>Sept.</hi> 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Caſſills</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arch. Johnſtoun</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Cheiſlie</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ro. Barclay.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>VVEe agree to the above written Articles, and do declare, that moſt of our Forces on this ſide of <hi>Tay</hi> ſhall be disbanded betwixt and the firſt of <hi>October</hi> next to come, and all of them on this ſide of <hi>Tay,</hi> without exception betwixt and the ſixth day of the ſaid Moneth, and likewiſe all thoſe on the other ſide of <hi>Tay,</hi> betwixt and the tenth day of the ſaid Moneth.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Subſcribed at Sterlin</hi> 
                     <date>27. <hi>Spet.</hi> 1648.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>W. Keith</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>J. Lyone</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hamilton</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>H. Berthwick.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
